A Guide to the Sherwood Anderson Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6181-a
Sherwood Anderson Collection 1923-1941
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6181-a
ca. 77 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 17 Dec 1963 shipment] 13 Feb 1964
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - No Swank and Other Moving Pictures, TMs, 115 p.
    [w/autographed corrections]
  - "Our City Small Towners", n. d.; TMsS, 6 p.
  - 12 poems from Mid-American Chants, n. d.; AMsS, 39 p.
    (Blank wrappers of same paper)
  - Begins, "Ten years ago when I began writing.. .", n. d.; AMSs, 8 p.
  - "When the Writer Talks", n. d.; TMs, 5 p.
    [w/autograph corrections]
  - "A Note on Realism", n. d.; TMs, 5 p.
- Letters
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1923 May 7; TLS, 1 p.
    [Sends novel with suggested title
    The Liar
    for publication; promises a shorter tale, "An Ohio Pagan," for the following week; mentions Carl van Doren. ]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto K. Liveright, [1923] May 9; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses publication of a story, trouble with the
    Pictorial Review
    , and business with Harper. ]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Reno, Nevada, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1923 May 14; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a book in progress; sends material for
    Harper's
    serial; asks him to call Mr. Canby about some material he was interested in; asks how he and Harper like
    Straws
    asks him to wire him, collect, in Reno as soon as has definite word from
    . ]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Thomas R. Smith, Boni & Liveright, New York, ALS, 1 p.
    [Hopes to do the "Dreiser Introduction"; needs [Theodore] Dreiser's
    Free and Other Stories
    as well as the "ante biography" to be sent to him in Reno, Nevada; requests copy of a book to which he contributed.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto K. Liveright, New York, ca. 1923 Jul 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends Dorothea Radin's translation of
    The Outpost
    by Boleslaw Prus; encloses a note to him from Mrs. Radin.]
  - Dorothea Prall Radin, Berkeley, California, to Sherwood Anderson, 1923 Jul 8; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses
    which has been returned from Putnam, Holt, Scribner's, and Moffat, Yard and Dutton; mentions that an English translation of
    has been published by Oxford University Press under the title
    Selected Polish Tales
    wants Anderson to send a copy of the book to Otto Liveright; gives particulars about the copyright, etc.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, [ New York], 1923 Dec 12; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a financial disappointment; says
    A Story Teller's Story
    has been turned down by Harper and he prefers for Huebsch to publish novel in book form, rather than submit it to
    Century
    regrets that Henry Canby's efforts have been in vain; feels that the literary world has not decided yet if he is a great man or a "flivver."]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, [ New York], 1923 or 1924; TLS, 2 p.
    and the possibility of getting it published by Harper; relates Henry Canby's remarks on the book; mentions the American Play Company and some business with it; makes disparaging remarks on [H. L.] Mencken and [George Jean] Nathan and their possible motivations should they take the book; hints that things in his personal life are at an impasse; feels good about a new story he has in the works.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, [ New York], 1923 or 1924; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a letter from Henry Canby, the Harper Publishing Co., the American Play Company, and short stories he has done (which he is putting aside to "ripen"); mentions his personal situation with T.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, [ New York], [1924 Feb 13]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Encloses an ingracious piece about him written by Ms. Gregory from
    The Dial
    as well as his reply to it; has received check from Liveright; asks for the February numbers of
    The American Mercury
  - Elizabeth Prall, Berkeley, California, to Otto and Bernadine Liveright, New York, 1924 Apr 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says she and Sherwood Anderson will be married the following day; talks about Anderson's improved health, their plans for the immediate future and travel plans if "Phantasms" come through in time; says they will come see Liveright in New York if they are able to travel.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, [ New York], [1924 Oct 27]; TLS, 1 p. w/autograph corrections
    [Thanks him for the good words about his book and for sending Mr. Wescott's book; says
    The Lovers
    will soon be ready and sent to Liveright; inquires about the book's serialization; mentions business with Harper, Century,
    fancies having a story of his made into a play; asks about possibilities regarding this idea; says he and his new wife are happy in Berkeley and about the reception of the book.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to Otto Liveright, New York, [1924 Nov 12]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Sends a story, the first of three; promises to send the novel in a few days; hopes the novel can be used as a serial.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New Orleans, to Horace Liveright, [1924 or 1923]; TL (initialed copy), 2 p.
    [Discusses his desire to switch publishers in order to sell more books; analyzes his feelings toward Ben [Huebsch] who supported him and published his books when everybody else turned him down; looks at his business relationship and friendship with Otto Liveright; feels his loyalty and friendship to his old supporters is stronger than the desire to make more money; urges Liveright to come visit him in New Orleans; mentions a good visit from Konrad, a writer.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Berkeley, to Otto Liveright, New York, [1924 Nov 15]; TLS, 2 p. w/autograph corrections and postscript
    [Discusses his guilty feelings after preparing to leave his publisher Ben [Huebsch] a year ago, how Huebsch accepted the books others rejected (
    Winesburg
    ,
    Many Marriages
    ), his plan to stick with Ben Huebsch with
    (which was rejected by Harper); realizes that his writing is too experimental to be a money-maker for any publishers; promises to send short story soon; suggests short story to be published in the Christmas number of the
    Berliner Tagblatt
    evaluates Wescott's book; mentions Liverights suggestions for the play.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Berkeley, to Otto Liveright, New York, 1924 Nov 20; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a new magazine and the possibility of the " Pittsburgh people" buying his new novel to be serialized; thinks it would be "a peach of a stunt for a new magazine," provided they have money.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Berkeley, to Otto Liveright, New York, 1924 Nov 20; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a clipping for [Konrad] Bercovia with a photo to follow, sad events in Liveright's life and rewriting of some chapters of the novel; comments on the book.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New Orleans to W. Orton Tewson, New York, 1925 Apr 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses refusal to review a book by his friend Alfred Kreymborg; does not like the book and would like to stay out of it; suggests review of new book by Ernest Hemingway, due to be published in fall; discusses work on a new novel to be ready for publishing in the fall.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New Orleans, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1926 Apr 19; ALS, 1 p.
    Vanity Fair
    "matter," progress with
    Tar: A Midwest Childhood
    , work on a new novel, imminent move to Virginia farm and health of his brother.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New Orleans, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1926 Apr 25; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses acceptance of offer from
    to write an article for a special issue (150 year anniversary of American) for $400.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1926 May 26; TLS, 2 p.
    check and interesting letter from Donald Freeman, editor of
    regarding future articles; suggests that Liveright negotiate for more per article from
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, Virginia, to Otto Liveright, New York, [1926 Jul 1]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses short story,
    "Another Wife"
    hope Liveright can sell it.]
  - H. L. Mencken, Baltimore, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1926 Jul 8; TLS, 1 p. w/autograph correction
    [Tries to buy story of Sherwood Anderson's for $325; discusses Anderson's support for
    in its early days and friendship between the two men.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, Virginia, to Otto Liveright, New York, [1926 Jul 13]; ALS, 9 p.
    [Discusses signing agreements for articles for
    , ideas for future articles and his idea of what Donald Freeman expects him to write about; mentions his relative isolation on the farm and his not reading many papers and magazines; mentions another story almost finished and the "Childhood Book."]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Jan 26; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions receipt of check, his writing form.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Feb 3; TLS, 1 p. w/ autographed addition
    [Discusses statement of money, made in 1927, for income tax and the endeavor to publish the best weekly in America. ]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Feb 24; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses the writing of "perfectly sexless story" for a female editor of a magazine for $500.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Mar 16; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses one of his stories which is in the possession of Arthur Vance and the possibility of it being published in
    The Caravan
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 May 1; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a "real" story; suggests sending it to "our prize lady magazine editor" and trying to get "some real money out of her."]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928 May 18]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses returning the
    contract to Liveright; refuses to write on just any subject suggested by editors; wishes to have wider latitude by having lots of subjects suggested; discusses "The Last Novel," to be used by Liveright for $500.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928 Jun 5]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses articles for
    , preference to reserve his own book rights, work in progress and a short story ready for sale.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Henry Goodman, Brooklyn, New York, 1928 Jun 6; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Discusses Goodman's request that Anderson explain himself as an artist; offers to print both Goodman's letter and his reply in his local weekly paper, the
    Marion Democrat
    promises to send copy when printed.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Jul 17; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a story to be sold to Harper's if possible, another story to be sent shortly; reminds Liveright to try to sell stories to
    and Scribner's. ]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Sep 10; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses $600 sent to Liveright by Donald Freeman; requests that the money be sent without delay.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Oct 2; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions receipt of a check; discusses story "Among The Drifters" to be sent to H. L. Mencken and story "Fred" to be sold elsewhere.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, 1928 Oct 19; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses check from Donald Freeman for $600; requests that Liveright forward it to him immediately.]
  - Blanche Gregory, New York, to Sherwood Anderson, Marion, Virginia, 1928 Dec 4; TLS, 1 p. w/ANS
    [Discusses Grant Overton's request for Anderson's permission to use Anderson's photos for
    The Worlds Fifty Best Short Novels
    Anderson replies on same sheet granting request.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses his upcoming trip to New York and possibility of seeing Liveright.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses Alfred Dashiell of Scribner's, "The Last Novel," and
    related business.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses a prose poem, written on the train; suggests selling the poem to McCall's; says his recent interest is in doing stories in a lighter vein; hopes that Liveright might be able to sell them to magazines that pay "real money."]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses Grant Overton; suggests that he get permission from Viking Press; states that Viking Press charges for all reprints.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Otto K. Liveright, New York, [1928]; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discussing Grant Overton and Viking Press; says he is working hard and steadily.]
  - Sherwood Anderson to "Roger and Ruth," [ Pittsburgh], ALS, 13 p.
    [Speaks of his feelings for them, what their friendship means to him; quotes D. H. Lawrence; says he will not sell Ripshin Farm (as was planned?) but will live there in the coming spring; says access to the farm will be easier as paved road from Marion to Troutdale is under construction; says he has lived alone for two years and will go to the farm with a woman he loves, Eleanor, perhaps marry her, even if the idea is absurd; talks about difficulties with himself, human relationships; suggests possibility that the four of them live on the farm.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Marion, Virginia], to Roger Sergel, [ Pittsburgh], [1923]; ALS, 4 p.
    [Invites Sergel family to come to Troutdale to talk about the play and other things; gives travel instructions; discusses attempt, apparently failed, to dramatize
    Winesburg, Ohio
    in collaboration with Arthur Barton and Louis Gruenberg; mentions living arrangements at Ripshin Farm, difficulties he had with Barton, and his upcoming marriage to Eleanor Copenhuaer. ]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion, to Harold Mason, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1935 Jan 5; TLS, 1 p.
    [Requests that a review copy of
    No Swank,
    be sent to Bill Stewart, editor of
    To-Day
    states that, instead of expected 12, he only got 6 copies of the ordinary edition.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New York to Miriam Phillips, Moylan-Rose Valley, Pennsylvania, 1937 Apr 26; APCS (initialed), 1 p.
    [Discusses a hat of hers she left in his car; his memory of
    "Twelfth Night"
    wishes to see [Yeats].]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, Virginia, to Miriam Phillips, Moylan-Rose Valley, Pennsylvania, 1937 Jun 8; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses the beauty of Ripshin farm in June; invites her and Jap [ Jasper Deeter] and Joe to visit; mentions his last visit to Hedgerow Theater, rumors about an amateur theater group in New Orleans and the possibility of its closing down because of homosexual involvement of the director with actors.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale to Miriam Phillips, Moylan-Rose Valley, 1937 Jun 21; TLS, 2 p. w/autograph comment
    [Mentions his presence at farm, their possible visit, her trip to Harrisburg; discusses the New Orleans Theater Company, possibility of their doing one of his plays, Mark Antony's scheduled visit to Ripshin, his almost finished book of three plays, the use of an essay he wrote on Jap [ Jasper Deeter] as an introduction to the book in the way of a dedication, possibility of the Winesburg play going into a repertory at the Hedgerow theater, the marketing of a new book; mentions his wife Eleanor's activities (attending "working girls conference"), and Mary Emmet's visit to the farm.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Chicago, to Herbert Feis, [ Lawrence], [1938] Oct 25; ALS, 5 p.
    [Discusses praise for Robert Nathan's [
    Autumn
    ], gratitude for Feis having given him the book, Feis' stay in [ Lawrence]; makes statements about himself; mentions his purchase of a Ford and delight in owning it and plans to go to Mexico City after Christmas to paint if the money comes through.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, New Orleans, to Roger Sergel, [ Pittsburgh], [1938]; ALS, 3 p.
    [Describes trip from Virginia to New Orleans and the towns he saw on the way and theater scene in New Orleans; plans to travel to Mexico via Brownsville from New Orleans; mentions the dedication of
    Puzzled America
    to Sergel, if Sergel does not object.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, "at the mouth of the Rio Grande, " United States, to Roger Sergel, [ Pittsburgh], 1938 Mar 30; TLS, 2 p. w/autograph postscript
    [Describes the trip to Mexico, the impression the country and the people made on him and the country's history; discusses the exploitation by British and American companies, the anti-American feelings of the Mexican people and acquaintances they looked up in Mexico; mentions the Baron matter and his leaving it to the Author's League and his expectation to have to pay for having been foolish.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Olivet College, to Miriam Phillips, Moylan-Rose Valley, Pennsylvania, 1939 Jun 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Describes being a professor at Olivet College for three weeks and his class schedule; plans to go to Antioch College next; says he enjoys the experience.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Troutdale, Virginia], to Joseph H. [Maconnahey], May 19; ALS, 2 p.
    [Replies to [Maconnahey's] request that he name his favorite books for his students to read; finds answering difficult; suggests
    The Triumph of the Egg
    and
  - Sherwood Anderson, Hotel Chelsea, New York City, to Herbert Feis, TLS, 1 p. w/autograph addition
    [Discusses traveling to the Midwest for Moley's magazine
    , his absence from "Ripshin" farm when Feis visits; says his books have been translated into Russian, but he has received no royalties; wishes to talk to Bullett about it; discusses the dramatization of
    , the production of it that summer, his plans to go to New York, possible interest of the Russians in the play and movie "poor White" after his book with same name.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Marion, Virginia], to Otto K. Liveright, [ New York], TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses his new novel which Liveright did not like at first, likelihood that it will grow on him, sale of a short story and possible sale of serial rights of the new novel; says he has a story, "Come Again Man," in the works intended for
    says he is under financial stress because of money that did not come through; mentions ideas for two new books, tentatively called
    Another Man's House
    The Man of Business
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Troutdale, Virginia], to Otto K. Liveright, [ New York], TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions amusing story he hopes Liveright can sell for him, receipt of a "nice letter from Konrad"; finds himself in a recurrent state of depression which undermines his productivity; hopes that the worst is over for Liveright in his personal life.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, to Otto K. Liveright, [ New York], Saturday; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends a short story which he has "lifted" out of one of his books.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Marion Hotel, Marion, Virginia, to Otto K. Liveright, [ New York], ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses income tax statement; intends to write something suitable for Harper's, after they turned him down several times in the past; mentions winter climate around Marion; describes article on "sleigh-riding in the old days of the horses" he sent to
    , which will be published the next winter and another article he is going to send to
    Vanity Fair,
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Troutdale], to Otto K. Liveright, [ New York], TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses possibility that
    has sent money to Liveright, his need of funds to cover building expenses at Ripshin Farm which will be the most charming stone house when completed; mentions progress of novel.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, to [Margrette], ALS, 4 p.
    [Gives his opinion of her short story; says it "does not quite get up and walk"; disapproves of mixing themes in a short story, how she throws things out of gear, etc.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Troutdale], to "Dear Sirs", ALS, 1 p.
    ["Certainly I wish you grand success with [
    The Outsider
    ]. Sincerely, Sherwood Anderson. "]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, to A. U. [Rawler], ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines request to analyze one of his own stories; he finds the idea unappealing.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, [ Troutdale], to "Harry K[ ]", ALS, 1 p.
    [Finds himself unable or unwilling to advise him in a matter so vital.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Columbus, Ohio, to "My dear Miss Lane", ALS, 1 p.
    [Agrees with her suggestion.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, Troutdale, to Herbert Feis, Washington, D. C., 1941 Feb 17; TLS, 1 p.
    [Mentions his upcoming trip to South America on February 28; plans to study small towns in South Africa and to write about them for
    Reader's Digest
    requests passport applications and necessary information from Feis.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Proofs of No Swank, 1934 Nov; Proofs
  - Proof w/autograph corrections of article "The First Printing of Sherwood Anderson's Winesburg, Ohio", Proof
  - Wrapper from photograph of Sherwood Anderson fishing, 1938 Apr 16; Wrapper
    [Sent from Anderson to Robley Durham Stevens in Philadelphia; in Anderson's writing; includes two United States 2 cent stamps.]
  - Sherwood Anderson, fishing, [1938]; Photograph signed
  - Sherwood Anderson, Photograph signed